Finding Aid for St. James Episcopal Church, Detroit, Mich., Records 1923-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. James Episcopal Church, Detroit, Mich., records 1923-1993
St. James Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
1 oversize volumes
8 linear feet
Church located in the Brightmoor area of Detroit, Michigan. Vestry meeting minutes; administrative files; registers of services; registers of baptisms, burials, marriages, etc.; records of different church organizations; bulletins of special church services; yearly files of collected clippings, photos, and other materials regarding church activities.
9433 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group came as part of the records of the Episcopal Church, Diocese of Michigan (donor no. 1059 ). These records were received in 1993 and 2002. Additional materials received in 2006.
The record group is open for research.
Brightmoor in Redford Township was originally a housing subdivision opened in 1922 and situated on Grand River Avenue approximately one mile from the city limits of Detroit. The area rapidly developed, and in 1926, the area was annexed by the city of Detroit. The beginning of Episcopal church services in Brightmoor can be traced to a "church on wheels" driven by the Rev. W.F. Jerome. Later that same year of 1923, the first recorded Episcopal Church service was held in the Brightmoor Community Hall. The congregation moved again in 1923 to the Maccabee Hall on Burt Road. Then in 1924, St. James Mission (as the church was named) erected its own building on Burt Road.
The church grew rapidly and there was need for further expansion. But not until after World War II were plans made for a new church building to be located at West Outer Drive and Lahser. The building was completed in 1951 and St. James became a parish church with the signing of corporation papers.
At one time St. James had a membership of 1600 members, but this dropped to 140 in 1988. Because of declining membership and the cost of maintaining the facility, St. James disbanded early in 1993.
The records of St. James parish include vestry minutes, 1924-1993; baptism, confirmation, marriage, and burial records, 1926-1993; bulletins, administrative records; records of the Episcopal Church Women and other parish organizations; and photographs. This record group has been divided into nine series covering the period from 1923 soon after the church began conducting services until 1993 when the church members decided to disband.
Subjects:
Brightmoor (Detroit, Mich.); Church records.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Detroit.; St. James Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Churches.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; St. James Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Vestry Meeting Minutes 1924-1993
  - 1924-1931 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942-1972, 19 folders (Box 1)
  - 1973-1993, 8 folders (Box 2)
- Register of Services 1923-1992
  - 1923-1992, 1 folders; 11 volumes (Box 2)
- Registers of baptisms, communicants, burials, marriages 1926-1993
  The registers of Baptisms, communicants, burials, marriages total ten volumes and date from 1926 to 1992. Included in this series is a card file index to the volumes.
  - 1926-1992, 9 volumes (Box 6)
  - 1932-1963 (Volume 1)
  - Card File Index
    - A-K (Box 7)
    - L-Z (Box 8)
- Administrative Records 1924-1993
  Administrative Records, covering the years 1924-1993, documents specific administrative functions within the church. Included are applications for baptisms, burials, lay ministers, membership transfers, and marriages. The church budgets in this series help to explain the finances of the church. The building fund files serve to document both the erection of the church's different facilities as well as its fund-raising capabilities. This series also contains correspondence relating to the closing of the church in 1992-1993.
  - Applications
    - Baptisms 1990-1992 (Box 3)
    - Burials 1990-1992 (Box 3)
    - Lay ministers 1973-1992 (Box 3)
    - Letters of transfer 1975-1993 (Box 3)
    - Marriages 1954-1965 (Box 3)
  - Budgets 1977-1988 (Box 3)
  - Building Funds
    - Campaign for education addition 1956 (Box 3)
    - Campaign for new church building 1950 (Box 3)
    - Rectory blueprints and decorating specifications 1960 (Box 3)
  - Chart of church accounts 1992 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - re. Church closing 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - re. Restoration to communicant status 1954-1958 (Box 3)
  - Instructions and procedures (Box 3)
  - Parochial reports 1978-1992 (Box 3)
- Church Organizations
  Church Organizations consists mainly of minutes of such church organizations as the Girls Friendly Society and the Young Peoples Society. Covering the years 1929-1992, the series demonstrates the importance of women in the church.
  - Episcopal Church Women (ECW)
    - Board Meeting Minutes
      - 1962-1965 (Box 3)
      - 1983-1985 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1983-1985 (Box 3)
    - Treasurers' reports 1962-1965 (Box 3)
  - Girls Friendly Society Meeting Minutes 1929-1932 (Box 3)
  - Safe Haven Program 1992 (Box 3)
  - Women's Auxiliary Minutes 1952-1963 (Box 3)
  - Young Peoples Secretary Book 1929-1932 (Box 3)
- Church Bulletins (special services) 1964-1992
  - 1964-1969 (Box 3)
  - 1970-1976 (Box 3)
  - 1977-1992 (Box 3)
- Yearly Activities 1926-1977
  Yearly files of clippings, photographs, and other materials describing church activities and events. This series covers the years 1926-1977.
  - 1926 (Box 4)
  - 1932-1947 (Box 4)
  - 1950 (Box 4)
  - 1951-1953, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1955-1977, 21 folders (Box 4)
- Photographs
  Photographs consists of photographs of church events such as the cornerstone laying and other building related services, confirmation photos, and portraits of the men who have served as rectors of the church.
  - Church events (cornerstone-laying, etc.), 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Church groups (Box 4)
  - Confirmation photos 1955-1987 (Box 4)
  - Church rectors
    - 1930-1959 (Box 4)
    - 1964-1989 (Box 4)
- Membership cards (Box 5)
  The final series, Membership, contains cards with information about congregation members, such as family names, dates of marriage, number of children, and addresses.
  - Membership cards (Box 5)